howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to gym
rut show.com
that's Jim ruts show com this is another
of our extra koban 19 episodes the sound
quality won't be as good as our regular
ones but the ideas will be coming fast
and furious today's guest is simon de
deo an assistant professor in social and
decision sciences at carnegie mellon
university and on the external faculty
at the Santa Fe Institute he was also by
the way the very first guest on the Jim
Rutte shows if you want to go back and
see episode one that was Simon we had a
great great conversation the reason I
invited Simon onto the show for one of
these short extra episodes is he wrote a
little paper one of the Santa Fe
Institute transmission series of short
papers about koban 19 it was titled
getting the quarantined endgame right
means thinking about how to change
thinking itself
Simon's say some more hi Jim it's a good
to be back on with you just for this
short little chat were having today this
was a piece that came to me in part cuz
I was talking to an old friend of mine
Michael Chan who lives in Hong Kong and
he was telling me about how they were
handling our had handled the SARS
epidemic in the past and one of the
things that struck me is that okay you
know at first to quarantine absolutely
you know you you wait for this thing to
stop spreading so that your risk is
maybe going down a little bit you're
staying out of the out of the out of the
wind but eventually you have to get back
into real life and in order to do that
you have to figure out who you're gonna
spend time with you have to figure out
you know who your kid's gonna go on play
dates with you have to figure out what
kind of risk you're willing to take and
when you do that you're gonna have to
use a set of heuristics about you know
your sense of risk but then also the
sense you have of the people you're
thinking about spending time with what's
their sense of risk how cautious have
they been how careful are they how well
do they watch their kids or their kids
as risky as as they you know as you fear
that kind of thing so it started me
thinking that we're gonna have the same
problem here the world has changed at
least for now and you know we're asking
ourselves questions that would have been
helped at the very least Jim I think
really offensive to ask you know a month
ago the idea that you wouldn't spend
time with somebody because you were
afraid they'd have picked up some
horrible disease and it was gonna kill
you that just wasn't on our radar I know
it is and so I was trying to figure out
okay what what kinds of social norms
arise around risk management for disease
and that's a little bit more than you
know what's the epidemiologically best
practice way of handling your social
life because you also when you're making
these decisions about who to spend time
with you also have to make your excuses
right so if you judge someone to be high
risk and you don't want to spend time
with them but you're otherwise that's a
socially connected to them what kind of
excuse
do you give right how do you explain
yourself to others when you're making
the kinds of decisions that in some
sense we've never been able to we've
never had to make before at least in our
living memory yep that's a very good
question you know and the other thing
that you know it kind of plays into this
one of the biggest takeaways I've
personally had from this experience is
the astounding cognitive diversity of
people who what I would have thought at
a high level at least were fairly
similar
you know people about my age you know
about similar levels of education etc
some of them were still going out to
dinner a week ago right you know others
of us locked down you know three and a
half weeks ago some people you know are
still not taking it all that seriously
some of the some of the rest of us or
you know every time we go out we have
masks and gloves and raincoats on and
the the spectrum is quite wide right and
that's a big AHA for me we were all
presented with the same evidence
you know I've argued on some of these
extra shows before that there's probably
a distinction between people who know
how to think exponentially and those
that don't but there's other things too
there's you know the Big Five
personality models there's probably you
know people who are more risk takers I'm
known to be a high risk taker but
nonetheless I've reacted very quickly I
believe strongly to this and the other
one I've noticed interestingly has to do
with our InfoSphere that those who I
would say are on the political right
were were late to get it even if they
were smart enough and educated enough to
have the cognitive tools to get it
because for a while the you know
transmitter in chief on that side was
not taking it seriously so that was kind
of interesting how people became their
views of a factual situation became
entrained by the mutterings of a shall
we say less than sharpest knife in the
drawer it's interesting Jim I mean those
that you're bringing up some really
great questions here I mean just on the
on the overall point of you know who who
was seeing this coming who was reacting
in ways that you know looking back a
year from now we'll say were the right
ways to do it you know part of this was
I think down to the capacity of the
imagination people who were willing not
just to imagine but I think also to act
on their imaginations were the ones who
were I think more cautious ahead of time
they really will look back and will say
yeah
one of things is funny first Jim is that
you know imagination is not always a
blessing right it could also be a curse
one of the things that I noticed and
it's
just completely informally is the people
who are really out in front of this
we're all the conspiracy theorists on
the right wing so if you don't used to
go all the way past what we think of as
the sort of median right and get way out
of the conspiracy theory world those
folks are actually you know like pretty
much in line with the epidemiologists so
yeah Steve Bannon was one of the first
people to get to understand it it was
amazing right exactly yeah so you know
along with the worldwide Jewish
conspiracy you know like if you could
imagine that you've got a lot of
capacity there the other thing you bring
out generous of course right there you
know that the you know imaginations of
course not the only quality right
there's you know the extent to which for
example you trust your reason but all of
those factors have meant precisely that
you know we're not on the same page
collectively and beyond that we're not
even on the same page within our social
circles where we usually are right so
you know in my social world Jim and I'm
sure in yours right you don't drive home
drunk right that's just that's off the
table right we all have a general
consensus about you know the right
spectrum of behavior we have for driving
so that's just that's just we we don't
even have to think about it right we
don't have to have that discussion we
don't have to think we don't have to
sort of judge whether or not somebody's
gonna be a dangerous driver that sort of
thing that's pretty much how our world
usually works but you know given the
extent to which we're not in agreement
and maybe we ought not to be an
agreement right now because I think you
know the most certain thing is the high
level of uncertainty but given we're not
in agreement how do we how do we
navigate this sort of very out of
equilibrium social environment it's not
something that that we're very familiar
with it's not something that we're
familiar with personally and I would say
also it's not something that the social
sciences are very familiar with indeed
in fact you know folks I'm talking with
we are now using the model that there's
been no shock like this to the United
States since World War two it's you know
it's interesting right because in terms
of existential threat right we're doing
okay right you know we're not going to
be speaking kovat and you know three
years
but in another sense absolutely it is a
it's a it's a huge social hit and it may
be more of an epistemic hit right then I
don't know a logical one
most of us are not at risk from this
disease I mean we we worry about it but
what we're really facing I think is is a
sort of dual problem what is the
uncertainty about the biology but the
other thing that I think we haven't
talked as much about but you're on this
wave luncheon which is wonderful is
we're also really uncertain about the
people around us right you know your
your quarantining I'm quarantine and you
know Carnegie Mellon is on board with
this right so I'm not in trouble for not
coming in to work I would be in trouble
if I tried to come into work now but you
know the broader world that we're
sitting inside of you know there's a
huge diversity of approaches and I think
most of us you know if we go downtown
you know to pick up some groceries
we'll see a huge spectrum of beliefs
about how we ought to respond and so
we're we have an epistemic uncertainty
about what's going on in someone else's
head not just what's going on you know
with the virus itself absolutely and
that's as I said my single biggest
unexpected learning from this is how
vast that cognitive model difference is
between people who are sort of otherwise
similar that's like when staggering to
me to me you know to me the evidence is
just stone-cold clear if you can do it
you should absolutely isolate yourself
to the maximum degree but a lot of other
people just don't see it that way of
course I will say part of it is you know
where you stand is is what you see as
somebody you know in the lower end of
the age danger belt I have a different
risk profile than a 22 year old so one
should expect that you know assuming
that they are a sociopath at least once
you'd assume that they would have a
different behavioral pattern than me but
I suppose that's the part that's
disturbing the sort of implicit
sociopathy right you say all right you
know I'm 23 years old and I'm a you know
a fraternity boy jock my chances of
having a bad outcome from this or pretty
damn low so I'll just go and hang out at
the beach party and lick the eyeballs of
the cheerleaders at all they
I usually do but they don't consider
their social obligations to not transmit
you know not to make our zero two and a
half instead of one point one which has
a gigantic downstream effect on people
who are more vulnerable so I expect
casual sociopathy is much higher than
one might think
well I think this is you know this is
this is a kind of combination of two
things Jim right you know the I mean I
think I probably saw the same video
right of that of the Florida bro you
know I catch cold I catch Cove it what's
gonna happen but there's sort of you
know there's there's a kind of second
step here I mentioned this in the paper
but you know right when this was kicking
off I was talking to a friend of mine
here he teaches philosophy became and
yeah I was like look in any other you
know year you know any other month of
the this in this world if I had told you
hey I read some stuff on Twitter and now
I'm staying inside my house I'm not
leaving right this would be a very bad
sign for my mental health right there be
heated clearly I had made some bad
judgments that day and somebody or
something had gone wrong are you done so
very bad drug I did some great exactly
so you know all of this standard you
know rules of thumb that we're using as
a kind of check on our own thinking
right the kind of you know error
checking we usually do right I come to
this conclusion but let me just you know
check it for sense all those sense
checkers aren't working right now
because those sense checkers operate on
a background of normalcy so you know we
have to you know our our ethical
judgments I suppose the right way to say
our ethical judgments are being convolve
door being stuck into a set of you know
pretty abstract chunks of reasoning
right reasoning about our non and
Exponential's whether or not the Florida
bro who you know gets on the TV and say
I'll catch Kobe whatever whether or not
that guy is you know actually a
sociopath or not it's clear that he
thought the social norm was that this
wasn't a problem right so you know maybe
this guy also you
gets drunk and drives home but he's not
gonna say that on public television
because he knows he ought not to do that
even if needed well we can see I think
in that in that television interview is
not just that the guy is you know not
thinking straight and maybe kind of an
ass but also that the wider norm hasn't
kicked in yet simply because he felt
that was okay he had no sense that that
was something he ought to be ashamed of
saying yeah and and that to your point
you know we're in a in a place where the
usual checksums don't apply right we're
inventing them dynamically on the fly as
our understanding that when that was
amazing thing from that seminar
yesterday even the greatest experts
gigantic error bars on all the main
parameters even now all right and so
people who typically have never thought
for themselves okay this is entering
this is an interesting road maybe this
is the the real distinction the large
number of people who never think for
themselves who essentially only react to
local social norms and essentially
follow their nose through life if they
have not yet received a signal they're
not going to do anything on the other
hand people who have always been in the
business I've been this way since I was
an obnoxious nine-year-old who think for
themselves right you know my mother said
oh yeah from the time you were 18 months
old you were one of those you're not the
boss of a kid's right and you know we've
always thought for ourselves I'm sure I
know here the same and so we were
processing the data that we got off
Twitter that we got off prowling the the
web and the CDC databases endlessly and
we said ah this is an exponential AHA
there are more than four hotspots in the
United States
aha with the testing rate is way lower
than it should be aha therefore the
incident rates at least 10x what's being
reported ah we're fucked right and some
of us came to it four weeks ago some
three weeks ago but certainly two weeks
ago we were all there
but the other folks who have to wait for
somebody else to figure it out and for
it to propagate as a social norm are
gonna lag I think that's the model what
do you think of that well you know Jim I
I may be a bit like and I'm a I have a
maybe slightly greater confidence in
my fellow man in the sense that I think
people actually do do a great deal of
thinking for themselves and I mean you
know a lot of day to day life absolutely
social norms are things you know you and
I don't think about we just do it right
I don't have to think about you know how
to interact with my neighbors on a
regular day I think the average person
who ever even if that phrase makes sense
right real extraordinary but you know
let's take someone who runs a small
business you know
in order for that to work it's a
complicated you know chunk of stuff you
do have to think for yourself maybe not
in a technical domain maybe not in a
mathematical domain but you're
constantly solving problems that require
creative thinking just maybe not the
creative thinking that's particularly
useful if you're looking at a
spreadsheet of cases let's say so I
think we shouldn't under eight the
capacity of our fellow citizens for
being able to think and for being able
to think for themselves and for you know
being able to reason
the unusual thing is that I think we're
asking people to reason in a domain that
you and I are pretty familiar with
correctly qualitative domain but that
they've never really had to encounter
before so I think that's really the the
issue here it's not between people who
think for themselves people who don't
think for themselves but the kind of
thinking for oneself that I think we
have to do now or at least we have to
get comfortable with is one that I think
most people aren't you see this a little
bit it's it's funny I was you know let's
talk about great minds learning to think
a different way I've been reading the
William Manchester biography of
Churchill right so Churchill is like the
least numbers guy of all time but you
know by the time World War two rolls
around right this guy is you know he's
really good at calculating tonnage right
he's learned to think about you know
shipping in a way that before that whole
crisis began it was not something that
was great so I think we're in any more
partial agreement here Jim I only got so
that's probably a fairer way to do it
but yeah the people who aren't used to
thinking quantitatively don't even
understand
concept of an exponential and I will say
just scream to me when I was talking to
you know friends and family oh there's
only 13 cases here in state why I go
yeah and if it doubles nine times what
do we have right these don't think that
way so you're right it's probably
they're not they're just not prepared
don't have the tools to think about
Exponential's and complicated scenarios
like this and then particularly if
they're embedded into place let's say
with people who are getting the
broadcasts from the oh this is not a big
deal this is just the flu plus then but
you know they don't look out looking for
signals elsewhere absolutely no I think
that's dead-on I think that's pretty
good
are you ready to you want to go jump out
into the void a little further let's do
it let's do it well I you know one of my
things I've been talking about on these
extra shows is the distinction between
homeostasis and hysteresis you know that
a complex social biological system has
two tendencies when once when shocked
one homeostasis to return to its
previous state and clearly there's a
strong lie beto for that and a lot of
the management and management we talked
about earlier before the show about the
backside of the curve a lot of is aimed
at homeostasis on the other side
hysteresis you know as a physics concept
systems that are given a shock now
become significantly determined by the
shock itself and don't tend to return to
equilibrium I suspect that this post
Koba 19 world's gonna be a mix of
homeostasis and hysteresis do you have
some ideas on where the system will not
return to the previous state okay we're
on the boy you're not responsible this
is not professional work this is Jim and
Simon bullshitting well so let me they
make a better point very quickly Jim
before I before I you know do the harder
thing of making a point you know that
that kind of question you're asking is
is you know a question that many people
in my social world and yours too I'm
sure
finding you know fascinating scary and
also potentially exciting
and it's sort of awful to have you know
any kind of positive sense for the
crisis we're having because people are
dying
but there isn't this is a moment for
people to think a little bit differently
about you know what kinds of equilibria
we want to come out the other side being
inside of you know we came out of World
War two with a set of institutions many
of which were extraordinarily functional
we came out the other side with let's
say an expanded public education system
you know we built the modern state
university as part of that so no one
would say World War two was a good thing
you know would prefer it not to have
happened but what we did with that with
some imagination was was pretty
remarkable so I'm I'm I'm all in favor
of asking the hysteresis question and
I'm also in favor of maybe asking it you
know in a positive sense to say well you
know what do we want coming out the
other side yeah absolutely agree that
there are huge numbers of positive
possibilities are also some negatives
but hey let other people dwell on the
negative let's think about the positive
one so do you have some positive ideas
let me think for a second here Jim you
know fair enough well let me let me let
me let me kick something out there Jim
and this is something that you know
we've I've noticed just really clearly
somebody said of the all of these blog
posts that are coming out from
corporations that have done all of this
in formal contact tracing so you'll have
some companies say check it out look
real will show you how all the guys on
Florida spring break where they went
the next night where they went the next
month and how they spread out over the
country right so they have these
wonderful kind of heat maps right
somebody pointed out Wow like every
company is now reframing the extent to
which they've been capturing
high-resolution data on our behavior as
a social positive right so you know
if a company you know two months ago had
said here's our map of where everybody
is going right now
we would have been horrified now we're
sort of impressed and you know maybe
slightly you know pleased that that map
is there one thing that's done I think
is you know really hit home for
everybody in the country something that
you and I have probably known for a long
time which is that there is no such
thing as privacy anymore you know we
might try and you know edge around
government restrictions we might say
okay we don't want the government to
keep this but you know every corporation
that has any kind of social media
contacts any kind of anything that runs
on a smartphone is gathering so much
data that you know your life is tracked
my life is track maybe you're maybe not
yours or maybe you're able to disconnect
but you know most of us we just can't
you know we've we've signed some
agreement we've clicked through some
agreement I think people now realize
that they realize that we just we have
no electronic privacy you might call it
child said we know childhoods end I like
that yeah because you know I was
involved in businesses that did direct
mail in the 90s where you could buy for
10 cents two hundred and seventy data
items on anybody you wanted and so I
knew in 1995 there was no privacy but of
course now we go even further to the
dynamics of where we hard any given
place in time I mean yeah and you know
what's mean everything down to you know
what's in our brain right one of the you
know one of the things that hit me years
ago was when I learned that you know if
you type something in the in the search
box in Facebook but don't click return
Facebook still captures that like they
can see what you typed and decided not
to send my type in fuck face Zuckerberg
don't hit return he gets the message I'm
gonna do that yeah we know this because
there was a terribly ill-judged
article by some academics who worked
with Twitter who looked at the tweets
that people decided not to send which we
should probably have more buts okay mean
that's that's the back
around here right now we all know and I
think there might be a really
interesting question coming out the
other side which is people saying okay
this data is here we now it's
unavoidable that we know you haven't we
also know that it can be used for good
as well and we may see a to me somewhat
unimaginable shift in you know from
privacy advocates who say you know get
out of you know delete everything about
me not possible to another sense of well
I have this data it belongs to me and
okay fine I want this to go here I want
this to go there but I don't want it for
that I want it for this the sense that
the data we have on ourselves is now
maybe some kind of public good we're
kind of public good that we haven't
really seen before it's a sort of a
dangerous one powerful something we want
some people to use for some purposes but
not others so we may add this may be a
mark of our some new kind of maturity in
the information age where we start to
develop we start to think really clearly
not just technically about what the fact
that you know you and I are shedding
terabytes of data a day I love it that's
a beautiful insight when I have not
heard from anybody else
and it's a classic example of hysteresis
you know we had this you know this
resistance around perceived privacy even
though we both know it's not true but a
lot of people acted as if it was or at
least we wish we could recover it
Paradise Lost we've now actually seen
the good that this can do and it will
you know beg some questions like maybe
we have there is a there is this data
this dynamic movement data but it's
escrowed only to the epidemiology
directorate or something right we know
it's hugely valuable for that but we now
when we see it in operation we know it's
also hugely subject to abuse and all
kinds of way so to make us think about
this in a radically different way that
is frankly more realistic than though
then the stupid dialogues back and forth
like you say I don't want all my data
lead it right wrong not gonna happen
yeah yeah that's a good I have you know
I often use a more prosaic one which is
that I suspect that with business travel
we'll never come back
I'm not to say it'll totally go away but
it wouldn't surprise me to find that you
know airplane business travel falls by
50 percent in a year or two after this
thing is over because this has been a
potentiality for the last ten years you
know since Skype basically now zoom and
WebEx and all this stuff the stuffs damn
good and it's damn cheap and you know
business travel you know me flying to
California and to have a two-hour
business meeting with somebody and then
come back three days out of my life
$2,500
waste of time energy and effort we could
have gotten to have a lot more done with
to to our zoom calls but we were we're
kind of locked into this signaling
behavior you know game-theoretic
signaling behavior I'm showing you
respect my Florin out to you and sitting
down talking to you about the business
deal here but now but now that we do it
by Zuma go shit this is so much more
efficient I was also talking to another
professor at another well-known
University and he was saying some pretty
heretical things he says you know my
classes are actually going better on
zoom' than they did in person the kids
are way more willing to ask questions
they seem much more engaged and of
course I make them keep the video on so
I can tell if they're paying attention
or not I'm not sure I want to go back to
live lectures you know what a radical
thought that might be you know that's
that's interesting Jim I mean it's I you
know 50 percents a pretty pretty big bet
I don't know if you've made some
investments in Airlines on the basis of
it I voted against I fortunately didn't
have many in my portfolio but I cleared
out a little bit I had and I've also
cleared out all mid-tier hotel chains oh
wow okay there you go
so let me let me let me follow up on
this right it's you know to me it makes
total sense I I love my colleagues in
Europe I love Europe
you know I was meant to fly out to give
some lectures in Austria that was
obviously canceled and I was like wait I
now have like four days to do something
else and you know
I was gonna give four hours of lectures
max maybe so you know that's a that's a
pretty inefficient way to use time and
secondly use Karma
but let's flip it around and say okay
fine we we stop all of our useless
travel so what happens instead right
what what do we do with you know what
does the you know frequent-flyer gag do
with all that spare time what do we do
if we're not you know flying to give
talks every month or flying for business
meetings every month what what do we do
with all that time that's a great
question hopefully we use it to improve
the world or improve our business or
improve our research or improve our
marriages but on the other hand we might
spend it smoking dope and playing video
games it's up to us it's yeah I mean
there's I know that I think the zoom I
don't know you know the zoom area is I
mean from the point of view of the
educator you can run a seminar on a
computer and honestly you're not gonna
miss much you know I used to take
classes at Saint John's back in Santa Fe
which I love it's you know that's you
sit in a seminar for three hours and
focus intently but you know it's not
like we're not touching each other we're
just sitting in chairs around a table
there's again with a you know slightly
better interface I'm not sure we need it
to be there in person but then what does
that do Jamie we're we're gonna do all
the real estate that's owned by the
universities that make it to the
homeless shelters really fancy really
fancy expensive ones that have banging
pipes right I think these are examples
of potential histories that things could
change in a fairly major way because we
think about these fancy universities
that we a lot of us went to you know
they're now one like what the hell they
cost two hundred and fifty three hundred
thousand dollars a year for a four-year
undergraduate degree what the fuck right
maybe they'll this will also provide a
way to rethink all of that so okay one
thing I predict is Harvard's you know
tuition will not drop
okay that's Harvard Harvard won't but I
you know it's always been we're on the
curve can you get away with hosing
people so that you can build up a twenty
billion dollar endowment right and it
falls off pretty quickly but you know
today it's like a hundred places they
can fuck you good it may be it's only
twenty places that can fuck you good in
the in the post-crisis world and so then
okay I mean if you if you were to play
that at gym right you know a major
socialization for whatever the middle
class up right is there for years
drinking at a university so if that's
not happening online you know its
potential it's it's possible that you've
decoupled your educational experience
from your social experiments that your
social world in their educational world
may actually become very different you
know that's a you know that's something
that affects a small you know fraction
of the country I don't know how many
people go to a four-year college in the
u.s. these days about about 30 percent
end up with a BS degree by the time
they're 30 35 percent something yeah I
mean that you know there's sort of four
year college experience from them from
the movies is becoming increasingly rare
yeah also keep in mind that so-called
elite colleges which goes including the
top you know University of Michigan
University
yeah university research universities is
only 10% of the BA so we're talking
three point five percent of Americans
have a four-year degree from a you know
Tier one research university right so
yeah I mean that's gosh I mean those are
I mean those are you know maybe I think
Jim one of the you know one of the
things we need in those cases is you
know more novelist to tell that story
because that's a you know kind of war
gaming the outcome of you know a
dramatic shift and how we produce the
elites right no longer sitting on a
campus that's that's a surprising shift
matter now to think about it that's cool
well Simon we're just about out of time
here we are I am I am I am dedicated to
keeping these things short do you have
any final thoughts or do you want to
just wrap it you've given me a lot to
think about Jim and I really appreciate
the time to just do a little imagination
as always with Simon it was interesting
one of my very favorite people
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jarred Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]